This is the story of the first ever use
of a weapon of mass destruction.
>> Very recently, the weapon we are about
to deliver was successfully tested in
the States. [music] We have received
orders to drop it on the enemy. It is
the most destructive weapon ever
produced.
>> The target was an empire with its own
secret weapon, the suicide bomber.
>> I trained myself that I could die at any
time.
>> On the 6th of August 1945, a bomb unlike
any other fell from the skies above
Hiroshima.
The bomb was designed by some of the
world's finest [music] scientists
using it as one of the most momentous
political decisions ever made.
>> Soldiers and sailors are the target, not
women and children.
>> This is the story of the air crew who
flew the mission and dropped the bomb.
I'm not thinking about the people that
got killed or hurt. I'm thinking about
the ones that did not get killed or
hurt.
>> And it's the story of the people of
Hiroshima who were the first ever
victims of a nuclear attack.
>> When something as devastating as a
nuclear weapon is used, people are
powerless. Just like ants or insects,
>> the entire city of Hiroshima was
annihilated in just a few seconds.
The bomb helped bring the Second World
War to an end, and it marked the
beginning of a new chapter in human
history.
July the 14th, 1945.
At the top secret research facility in
Los Alamos, New Mexico, a heavily armed
convoy was loaded with parts for a new
kind of bomb.
This was the start of a journey that
would end in Hiroshima.
This bomb was the product of 3 years
research and had cost $2 billion to
develop.
But at this stage, the technology was
still completely untested.
Two days later, there was a chance to
find out.
In the desert of New Mexico, the
scientists and soldiers of the Manhattan
Project gathered for the first ever test
explosion of an atomic bomb.
>> 100 to one, we crack the Earth's crust
and destroy the whole world. 50 to1, we
ignite the atmosphere and only destroy
New Mexico.
>> Someone should firm me up. He's
frightening the MPs.
>> 10 to one, it fizzles out. If that
weapon fizzles out, each of you can look
forward to a lifetime testifying in
front of congressional investigation
committees.
6 5 4 3 2 1 zero.
The explosion vaporized the steel tower
holding the bomb. The intense heat
melted the desert sand, leaving an area
of glass.
The force of the explosion was estimated
to be the equivalent of 67 million
sticks of dynamite.
>> [applause]
>> The bomb had originally been intended
for use against Nazi Germany, but its
backers now had another target in mind.
>> I'm very proud of you.
>> Thank you.
>> Well done. War's over, General.
>> Yep. As soon as we dropped a few of
these things on Japan.
Good work.
>> For scientific director Robert
Oppenheimer, it was a moment of terrible
truth.
>> Now I am become death, the destroyer of
worlds.
By July 1945, the war in Europe was
over. Nazi Germany was [music] defeated.
But in the Pacific, the war against
Japan was raging on.
After the surprise attack on Pearl
Harbor, American forces had fought their
way back across the Pacific, island by
island, with savage hand-to-hand
fighting,
but Japan's main armies were still
intact and undefeated.
The Americans had tried firebombing the
Japanese into submission.
City after city was reduced to rubble.
But still the Japanese refused to
surrender.
So the allies now faced the prospect of
a fullscale invasion with some estimates
putting their losses as high as a
million casualties and many more
Japanese.
In Japan at the time, the emperor was
head of state [music] and also a living
god. But day-to-day power rested with
the special war direction council.
Prime Minister Suzuki and Foreign
Minister Togo were considering a
negotiated settlement,
but Army Minister General Ketcha Anami
was determined to fight on.
Aname's plan was for an allout final
battle.
Fore!
Foreign! Foreign!
In Hiroshima, as in the rest of Japan,
soldiers and civilians were being
prepared for the coming invasion.
The Japanese military were relying on a
powerful weapon.
People's willingness to die for the
emperor.
Ordinary soldiers learned how to strap
bombs to their bodies and throw
themselves under tanks.
Dr. Shintaro Heda was working at the
army hospital in Hiroshima. One of his
duties was to train medical orderlys as
suicide bombers.
The soldiers were trained to strap bombs
to their bodies and throw themselves
against the tanks.
At the military hospital, we had to
teach this.
>> The officers in particular were resigned
to the fact that once we had gone to the
front, we would not return. we would
die.
>> I trained myself that I could die at any
time.
[screaming]
>> The whole population was to be part of
the battle against the invaders. [music]
>> Even school girls were trained to attack
American soldiers with sharpened bamboo
spears.
A blood bath seemed inevitable.
[screaming]
>> The man who would have to authorize the
invasion was American President Harry
Truman.
On the 16th of July, he had just arrived
in Berlin for the Potam Conference where
he was meeting his fellow allied
leaders.
>> Mr. President,
>> that very night came news of the
successful New Mexico bomb test.
>> Listen to this.
Operated on this morning, the results
seem satisfactory. The test has already
exceeded expectation.
They did it.
Now the boys may be spared an invasion
of the Japanese home islands. I'll drink
to that.
Truman soon received a more detailed
account of the test and [music]
discussed the news of the bomb with the
British Prime Minister Winston
Churchill. Then he decided to tell
Stalin. So on [music] July the 24th
after the plenary meeting had ended,
Truman took the Soviet leader aside.
On Truman's staff was a young naval left
tenant, George Elie, the last surviving
witness to these events.
>> He remarked to Stalin, "The United
States had a powerful new weapon." And
Stalin said words to the effect. He
hoped it would be put to good use.
>> We have developed a new very powerful
destructive weapon which we have tested
successfully. The exchange was so
low-key that Admiral Ley and Chip Bolan,
who was Truman's interpreter, weren't
sure that Stalin had understood, really
grasp the significance that a powerful
new weapon really meant such a weapon.
>> All he said was that he was very happy
to hear it and hoped we would make good
use of it against the Japanese. Of
course, at that time, nobody on our side
knew the depth of Soviet penetration
into Los Alamos and that Stalin knew
perfectly well what Truman was talking
about. The only thing, I guess, that
Stalin didn't know was that Trinity had
taken place. And it's possible that he
even knew that.
But before going ahead with the new
bomb, Truman gave the Japanese one last
chance [music] to surrender.
The Americans had broken secret Japanese
codes and could decipher military and
diplomatic cables.
So they knew their demands for total
unconditional surrender had been seen as
a threat to the emperor.
Now they decided to alter the terms and
give the Japanese a way out.
>> The pots dam declaration called upon
unconditional surrender.
It was modified in the light of this
what we were learning from the
intercepts to read unconditional
surrender of the armed forces of Japan.
We call upon the government of Japan to
proclaim now the unconditional surrender
of all Japanese armed forces. That left
the door open for a retention of the
emperor.
[music]
>> The modified ultimatum was broadcast to
Japan.
But ironically, the softening of the
surrender term seems to have backfired.
Prime Minister Suzuki announced that his
government would ignore the Potam
declaration.
He used the word mosatsu, meaning to
kill [music] with silent contempt.
From that moment, the dropping of the
bomb on Hiroshima was inevitable.
The bomb left San Francisco on board the
USS Indianapolis 2 hours after the
successful Trinity test in New Mexico.
It traveled across the Pacific on a
10-day voyage to the island of Tinian.
Just 6 hours flying time from Japan.
The island was the biggest air base in
the world with four large runways and it
was home to more than 500 B29
Superfortresses.
It was also home to the 509th Composite
Group, the men who would drop the atom
bomb on Japan.
In charge was commanding officer Colonel
Paul Tibbitz, a veteran [music] of the
bombing campaign against the Germans.
At 29 years of age, I was so shot in the
ass with confidence anything I couldn't
do.
The two key members of his crew were
Bombardier Tom Ferby
and navigator Dutch Van Kirk.
>> You never heard the word atomic,
nuclear, or anything of that type around
the group. We always referred to the
weapon as the gimmick, the weapon, uh uh
that sort of thing. And um if you did
figure it out, you better be smart
enough not to talk about it.
>> All right, gentlemen. Cities have been
signed off. Ioto is out. Stimson likes
the temples too much. But we've got
Nyaga, Kakura, Nagasaki, and Hiroshima.
The only major cities left we haven't
roasted.
>> And the primary?
>> The primary is Hiroshima. All right.
Have you worked out an aiming point?
>> T-shaped bridge here.
That's the most perfect AP I've seen in
this whole damn world.
>> Angle of approach, bomb drop like this.
Prevailing winds from the north. You may
want to come in this way. Then you'll be
flying with the wind and you'll clear
the target sooner.
>> Too risky. We'll fly into the wind. That
way we're slower and more accurate.
>> You may get caught in the blast.
>> Once I make the dive turn, I'll have a
tailwind. We'll be out quicker.
>> Anyway, we'll take that risk. We want to
be as accurate as possible, don't we?
>> Hiroshima was an important military
base, the headquarters of the second
general army with a key role in the
defense against the expected invasion.
Ako Takura, who was 19 and working as a
bank cler in the city center, remembers
the atmosphere at the time. People
called it an army city. Everywhere you
looked, you saw the army.
And there were always a lot of ships
transporting soldiers from the port.
All the major cities in Japan had
already been the targets of bombing
raids. So everybody living in Hiroshima
expected that Hiroshima would be
targeted soon.
What no one could realize was that the
city had been preserved for a reason.
The Americans had deliberately avoided
firebombing Hiroshima so they could
measure the precise effects of the atom
bomb.
On the evening of the 4th of August,
Paul Tibbitz called his men together.
The bombing mission was set for the
following night when the clouds [music]
over Japan were due to clear.
>> The moment has arrived.
This is what we've all been working
towards.
Very recently, the weapon we are about
to deliver was successfully tested in
the States. We have received orders to
drop it on the enemy.
>> There will be three possible targets. In
order priority, they are Hiroshima,
Kokura, Magasaki.
>> The bomb you're going to drop is
something new in the history of warfare.
It is the most destructive weapon ever
produced.
You think it's going to knock out
everything within a threemile area.
Roll film. Kill the lights.
>> Weapon specialist Deep Parsons had
brought film of the New Mexico
explosion,
but the projector jammed.
The uh film you're now not about to see
was made of the only test we performed.
I was in a B29 looking down on the
target in the darkness and I can say
that it is the brightest and the hottest
thing on this earth since creation.
This is what happened. The flash of the
explosion was seen for 10 miles. A
soldier 10,000 ft away was knocked off
his feet. Another soldier more than 5
miles away was temporarily blinded.
Those of us who were there knew it was
the beginning of a new age.
No one knows exactly what will happen
when the bomb is dropped from the air.
That has never been done before. But we
expect a cloud
this shape
rise to at least 30,000 ft, maybe 60,000
ft, preceded by a flash of light much
brighter than the sun.
A combat version of the bomb
has now been assembled and ready.
All we are waiting for is an end to the
rainstorms over Japan so we can see our
target, Colonel Tibbitz.
>> Right, men? I know some of you seen a
lot of action already, and I picked you
cuz you're the best available.
But let me tell you all, beside this
mission, whatever you've done before in
this war is small potatoes.
I am personally honored, and I'm sure
all of you are, to been chosen to take
part in this raid, which will shorten
the war by at least 6 months.
You're now the hottest crews in the Air
Force.
There will be no talking about this to
anyone.
No talking even among yourselves.
No letters, no writing home, no
mentioning of the slightest possibility
of a mission.
Is that clear?
>> Yes, sir.
The next morning, the air crews on
Tinion woke to a disturbing sound.
Once again, a B-29 had crashed on the
runway.
The crash alarm passens the [music]
weapon specialist.
It was the day of the mission and they
were planning to load the bomb onto the
plane fully armed.
The bomb's firing mechanism [music] used
gunpowder to force two separate pieces
of uranium together to start a nuclear
reaction.
Parson's worry was that if the plane
crashed on takeoff, [music] the firing
mechanism would be triggered and they
would blow up the whole island.
So without authorization, he changed the
plan.
>> I think it's better if I load the powder
charges into the gun barrel after we
clear the island.
>> Have you made the assembly with the
powder charges before? Do you know how
to do it?
>> Nope.
But I got all day and night to learn. We
don't take off low 200. There is time.
>> If Parsons got it wrong, there was a
serious risk the whole mission and the
bomb would be wasted.
>> Parson sat in that airplane for several
hours rehearsing exactly what he was
going to have to do. Removal of the
brereech plug, inserting the powder,
hooking up the thing. He made at this
time. This is when he made his detail
check off list
and he practiced that for half a day and
his his his hands were beaten up from uh
handling this thing. For God's sakes,
man, why don't you let me lend you a
pair of pigkin gloves?
>> I wouldn't dare. I got to feel the
touch.
Looks like we'll be bombing the jabs
with dirty hands.
Paul Tibbitz had reached a decision of
his own. As commanding officer, he was
also planning to pilot the strike plane.
As was traditional, he chose a name for
it.
I said, "I'd like to name it after my
mother. Her name is Inola Gay. And I
know that there'll never be another B29
or I don't think there ever be an
airplane flying that will have the name
Gay on it. I think the airplane will go
down in history. And I want to be with a
good omen."
>> Tibet's decision came as a shock to
Captain Bob Lewis. He had always flown
that plane and assumed he would be the
pilot.
Why the hell are they putting that on my
airplane? What's going on?
>> Well, number one, it's not your
airplane. It belongs to the United
States Army Air Corps.
>> Number two, I'm the organ I'm the
organization commander. I can do
anything I want with any
>> any one of those airplanes, including
yours.
>> Hey, shut up. That was that was the only
discussion.
>> Dismissed.
For most citizens of Hashima, the 5th of
August [music] was uneventful.
As the day closed, people prepared
themselves for more air raid sirens and
more disturbed sleep.
Dr. Hedo was still on duty after a busy
day. He remembers the fifth quite
clearly.
>> I returned to the hospital at around
8:00 p.m.
>> An officer on night shift came and told
me that four guests from Manuria were in
Hiroshima.
>> They were high ranking army doctors.
I was told to look after them.
Eventually, I put everybody to bed and
then I laid down beside them. [snorts]
Then, in the middle of the night, an old
man from the village came on his bicycle
to see me.
There weren't any doctors where he
lived. They were all at the front.
Thinking it couldn't be helped, I went
with him in the middle of the night. I
was very drunk.
There were no cars at that time. And so
I sat on the back of the old man's
bicycle.
>> That is how I survived.
Okay, there are three planes involved in
the mission.
>> That night, in the last minutes before
departure, there was a final briefing
for all the crews who were heading to
Hiroshima.
>> There are three planes involved in the
mission.
>> Number one, the Anola Gay carrying the
bomb.
Number two, the great artist
carrying the recording equipment.
Number three,
>> the necessary evil.
We were the photographic ship.
>> Do your jobs. Obey orders. Don't cut
corners.
That is all.
The mission was so secret, Tibetz was
given suicide pills in case they fell
into Japanese hands.
>> That evening when we came out of the
mesh hall, flight surgeon gave me the
pills. He told me what they were. I hope
you don't need them, but he said, "If
you do, they're cyanide." He said,
"Here, if you need them, one for each
man of the crew. He said, "You never
know anything. Within 6 minutes, you're
gone. You never feel anything different.
You never know a thing." I told the guys
outside the airplane before we climbed
up, "I'll give you any one of you a pill
if you want the pill." And uh nobody
said anything but Captain Parsons. He
said, "I'd like to have one." And I
understood his position cuz he he knew
more technical stuff about that bomb
than anybody.
When we got the Inola Gay, that was our
first big surprise because we had uh
there were lights all over the place and
everything, but this was unlike any
mission we'd ever flown before. You
know, it was like a Hollywood premiere.
>> Photographers and film crews had been
ordered to record the historic mission.
and we had climbed into the airplanes. I
want to start the engines and there were
people all around it. There were plague
lights right there right in front of the
number two engine and I couldn't do
anything with that thing there. So, uh,
I opened the window, stuck my head out.
I said,
>> "Stand back.
Move out of the way."
>> But I just waved my hand like that and
some guy says, "Wave at us." So, I
waved.
And that's what you got.
It was another day. It was another
bombing run and that was it. It was my
responsibility.
>> Dimples 82 to North Tinia tower. Taxi
out takeoff instructions.
>> 82.
>> The bomb weighed more than 4 tons,
making takeoff even more dangerous than
usual.
15 seconds to go.
>> In takeoff, I remember the most
dangerous part of flying is in takeoff.
>> 5 seconds.
Get ready.
>> Everyone on board, I'm sure, felt the
same way I did, waiting for for it to
lift off.
And it seemed like it took an inordinate
amount of time.
I wanted to hold the airplane on the
ground to get all the air flying over
the tail that I could get.
I held it down longer than what Bob been
used to seeing. And the airplane took
off at 140 45 mph. I held it down to was
over 150 mph and he reached for the
yolk, started to pull it back, said,
"Pull it back.
>> Pull it back now.
>> GET YOUR DAMN HANDS OFF THIS YOLK. I'M
FLYING THIS AIRPLANE."
>> And he pulled back right quick.
But eventually it lifted off and [music]
we didn't crash at the end of the
runway. We were off.
>> 15 minutes after takeoff, with the plane
still at low altitude, Parsons was ready
to assemble the bomb. They're starting
>> dimples 82 to North Dian tower. Judge
going to work. I repeat, judge going to
work.
>> It's about maybe 8 in wide around the
outside to the back end of the weapon
which had those big fins.
very cramped quarters. You had to squat
down in order to peer into the back end
of this bomb. And that's the position
that Parsons took is to work inside
these uh fins.
>> They all knew a mistake would jeopardize
the entire mission.
>> Unscrewing breach.
inserting charges. Jack
>> Parsons would then take the powder
charges about the size of a loaf of
bread that would he would put those in
there one at a time. Then he'd pick up
the breach block, put it in the where it
was supposed to go, turn it to make the
seal.
>> Inserting breach.
Each one of these maneuvers [music] he
would check off on his check off list to
ensure that he had made no mistakes.
>> And returning home, check.
>> 2 hours later, the Anola Gay met up with
the scientific and photographic planes.
They were now 3 hours from Hiroshima.
Dawn is breaking and it's us now. It's
just a beautiful, beautiful morning. You
know, look, we're at about 9,000 ft at
that time. And we all remarked about
what a beautiful sunrise it was that
particular morning.
Just want you guys to know we're
carrying a bomb so much power. We got a
good chance of ending the war in one go.
>> What is it, Colonel? Some kind of
chemist's nightmare?
>> Nope, that's not it. Some kind of
physicist's nightmare.
>> That's closer.
>> You say, Colonel,
>> are we splitting atoms today?
>> Yes, we are.
>> Dick Jeepson, Parson's assistant, had
one task left to arm the bomb. Before
the plane went to altitude, I had to
climb into the bomb bay and remove these
three green plugs and replace them with
three
arming plugs which enabled the fusing
circuit to fire the weapon causing it to
detonate.
And the only time I felt really nervous
on this mission was the time when I
inserted these red plugs into the bomb.
The bomb was now armed and live.
After they were in place, I breathed a
sigh of relief because nothing had
happened at this point in time.
Evidently, with the action of replacing
these plugs or switching these plugs, I
became the last person to put a hand on
this bomb.
I hadn't realized that at the time.
>> [music]
>> We're at 30,000 ft.
Ahead of the Anola Gay, another B29 was
already flying over Hiroshima, checking
the weather. It triggered an alert.
There was an air raid warning. It was
the type that warned that a raid was a
possibility.
As the people waited in air raid
shelters, the weather plane reported its
findings to the Anola gay by coded
message.
Cloud cover less than 3/10 at all
altitudes. Advice bomb primary.
>> It's Hiroshima.
The weather plane now headed away. For a
time, it seemed that the threat had
passed.
About 30 minutes later, they sounded the
all clear.
It meant there was not going to be an
air raid. So, everyone went about their
business going to offices [music] and
factories.
I think that was the reason why such a
large number died and could not be found
afterwards.
>> On the drill ground, thousands of
soldiers were doing their early morning
exercises. Among them, Cadet Mario Oaki.
American
planes often flew overhead without
dropping any bombs, but I had a feeling
that something would happen soon.
>> Dr. Heda had spent the night at a farm
outside Hiroshima looking after the girl
with heat stroke.
>> It was just after 8:00 when I woke up.
I was already late. I had to go back to
the hospital.
>> I got myself ready, took the child's
pulse, and then examined her chest with
a stethoscope.
16-year-old Tero Fuji had enlisted as a
tram driver to support the war effort.
>> The men were sent [music] to the front
with the army.
Because their numbers gradually
declined, they wanted students to drive
the trams.
Clark Akiko Takura and her friend were
the first to arrive at the bank in
central Hiroshima. Just 260 m from the
aiming point, the T-shaped bridge.
>> At the bank, I stamped the arrival book.
You would stamp next to your name when
you arrived. So, I stamped the book.
In those [music] days, female staff were
supposed to arrive 30 minutes before the
men to do the cleaning.
>> That sort of thing would be unthinkable
now.
>> Kinukoi was working as a nurse at the
communications hospital also near the
center of the city.
My first job of the day was to sterilize
the hospital tools and prepare the
patients for surgery.
>> The weather was beautiful. The sky
[music] was clear blue, not a cloud in
sight.
In another part [music] of the city,
8-year-old Takashi Tanamorei was on his
way to school.
>> Every morning, soon we get to school,
we're going to play the game, hide and
seek.
Then we starting picking who's going to
be it. And so we ran to the main gate
and I was become it that morning.
Shigay Hiatsuka died in [music] 2002,
but her extraordinary story is taken
from her written account.
It had just gone past 8 in the morning.
We had finished breakfast.
Our two children were playing beside us.
My husband was reading the newspaper.
Paul, Tom, Deac, and I are all three up
there confirming yes, this was a target.
Yes, that was bridge. Yes, that was the
aiming point. Might say we're having
convention up the nose of the plane.
>> Okay, we're about to start the bomb run.
Put on your goggles.
And we were on that bomb run for three
three and a half minutes now. Tom and I
are talking.
>> Christ Dutch, you never sat on a bomb
run this long over Germany. They'd have
blasted us OUT THE SKY.
>> YEAH,
>> he said nothing there. No opposition, no
nothing or anything of that type. Just,
you know, just going to bomb the target.
I saw an aircraft like a tiny silver
drop entering the sky. high above
Hiroshima.
I instantly recognized it as an American
plane
as no Japanese aircraft could fly at
that altitude at the time.
>> It was just one plane. So I assumed that
it was passing by as usual.
And I was counting
itchy.
>> I was wiping [music] the desktop. That
was when the bomb was dropped.
Wrong way.
In those days, soldiers were told to
take off their clothes to avoid damaging
them.
As it was the all clear, I went into the
barracks to take my shirt off.
Now, it took about 45 seconds from the
time the bomb left the airplane until it
exploded. And I think there wasn't a man
in the airplane that wasn't either
timing it with his watch or counting or
doing something. I was sure the bomb was
a dud. I was sure it wasn't going to
work.
After falling for 43 seconds, the time
and barometric triggers started [music]
the firing mechanism. A uranium bullet
fired down a barrel into a uranium
target. Together, they started a nuclear
chain reaction.
Solid matter began to come apart,
releasing untold quantities of energy.